A Guide to the Papers of the Women's Council for Interracial Cooperation 1959-1961
Special Collections, Perry Library, Old Dominion University
Special Collections, Perry Library, Old Dominion University
The Papers of the Women's Council for Interracial Cooperation 1959-1961
Special Collections, Perry Library, Old Dominion University
MG 54
One Hollinger Documents Case, .5 linear ft.
Administrative Information
Access
Open to researchers without restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Donated to Old Dominion University in 1982 by Mrs. H. M. Silverman, the President of the Organization from 1955 to 1957.
Biographical/Historical Information
On April 17, 1945, eight black and eleven white women met in the vestry room of Ohef Sholom Temple in Norfolk. Mrs. W.T. Mason had invited these women in order to consider forming an interracial committee. All the women present were active in civic organizations, and came from different religious backgrounds.
At that first meeting it was decided that such an interracial group could indeed be beneficial to Norfolk. Furthermore, they decided that their organization should be autonomous - not affiliated with any other organization, but working in cooperation with them.
Mrs. Mason was appointed temporary chairman and the group held meetings in May, June, and September. The first two meetings were devoted to establishing a constitution and coming up with a name. By December, there were 86 members.
Early in 1946, the WCIC was becoming active in the public school system, and worked with the public libraries and the Boy Scouts to notify the public of their humanitarian goals. These goals were:
.... to improve city facilities for education, recreation, employment, and health
.... to improve interracial attitudes
.... to seek equality of opportunity for everyone
.... to work towards full citizenship privileges for all
The WCIC implemented these goals by calling attention to the need for more blacks in civic occupations; worked with health organizations in providing testing for diseases and public health information; held public meetings and other activities with nationally known speakers to advance the ideas of integration; and met with city officials concerning proper housing for the poor. For the first two years the group met in different churches and kept their files and printed materials in the homes of its officers and chairmen. Finally the WCIC was able to get space for an office and meetings at the YWCA. This lasted for several years.
As stress in Norfolk over the desegregation of public schools reached a climax, the WCIC found itself pitted against many opponents of desegregation. It became more difficult to find meeting places open to such a group. Also, when they did find a place, they often could not advertise their meeting because of criticism and possible censure it would draw towards those who allowed such a meeting to take place at their establishment. Consequently, for a period of time, the WCIC worked more "behind the scenes" than in the public eye. However the effectiveness of the group endured and through their studies and reports of other cities with integrated school systems, the group helped Norfolk overcome the crisis in 1958 when the public high schools were shut down.
Scope and Content Information
The Women's Council for Interracial Cooperation (WCIC) was an organization of white and black women devoted to fostering racial harmony. The papers, dated 1959 to 1961, include the organization's constitution, minutes of meetings, correspondence, speeches, annual reports, member lists, booklets, pamphlets, programs, invitations, newspaper clippings and published articles. Of interest is a transcribed panel report titled, "How Norfolk Opened Her Schools," dated February 2, 1959 and Susan Slaughter's personal account of the "First Fifteen Years of WCIC." In addition, there is material relating to the inception and early history of the Human Relations Council, which superseded the WCIC.
Contents List
- Annual Reports, Constitution, Rules, Origins, etc. (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 1)
- Annual Report-Commission on Community Origins, etc. (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 2)
- Board Members and Other Lists (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 3)
- Board Minutes, September 14, 1960-April 18, 1961 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 4)
- Booklets and Pamphlets (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 5)
- Correspondence and Clippings-General Dwight D. Eisenhower (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 6)
- Correspondence-Senator Hubert Humphrey (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 7)
- Correspondence Concerning Printed Materials (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 8)
- Correspondence-Potential Speakers, 1951-1952 Season (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 9)
- Correspondence-Potential Speakers, 1952-1955 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 10)
- Correspondence-Miscellaneous and Undated (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 11)
- Invitations (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 12)
- Magazine Articles (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 13)
- Newspaper Articles, December 1957-November 1958 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 14)
- Newspaper Articles, January 1-January 20, 1959 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 15)
- Newspaper Articles, January 21-January 30, 1959 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 16)
- Newspaper Articles, January 31-February 21, 1959 and October 15, 1963-August 14, 1964 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 17)
- Newspaper Articles-Undated (circa 1959) (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 18)
- Norfolk Human Relations Council (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 19)
- Norfolk Story-"How Norfolk Opened Her Schools," February 2, 1959 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 20)
- Photograph-Ruth Danehower Wilson (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 21)
- Programs-Miscellaneous Events (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 22)
- Red Cross Certificate (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 23)
- Speeches (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 24)
- YWCA Material (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 25)